bugs in C++. Does that even happen?
Welcome to a new series in which we have
a look at various bugs that can happen
in C++ and hopefully help you avoid
them. Today we're going to be talking
about references and how maybe you
should be careful when you make
references to various things because
they might just not be as innocent as
they seem. Jumping straight into an
example. This is a very fabricated
example. You probably wouldn't write
code that looks exactly like this. But
can you spot the issue over here? So,
we're creating this brand new vector of
strings called fruits. Then, we're using
the push back function a bunch of times
just to add some elements to it. Again,
not exactly realistic. You'd probably
just write out the list, you know, in
the constructor as a static initialized
list. Ignore that. That's not what this
is about. And then, what do we have over
here? We have a variable called first
fruit that is a string reference. So,
we're just trying to have like a nice
name to refer to the very first fruit
inside this data structure. Seems
innocent enough. I don't want to have to
keep referring to fruits zero. I just
want to have this string reference that
is the first fruit so I can then maybe
print it later. But what's this? Uh I'm
actually going to add something else to
the collection first and then print the
first fruit. Doesn't that seem like it
would work? Well, let's run this code
and see what happens.
Oh, okay. So, it looks like we have some
read access violation. If we have a look
at the call stack, then it's all like
inside, well, it's inside the print line
function, but it seems to just not be
able to format the string correctly or
something. It seems a bit weird. And if
we go back up here, we can see that it's
happening as a result of this print line
because what are we trying to print?
First fruit error reading characters of
string. The size of the string is
apparently that big and it's just can't
read the characters of the string. What
has happened? Well, what we've done is
we've taken a reference to an element
inside this vector. How does that work?
Let's talk a little bit more about how
references work and what they kind of
are. I have a video about references in
C++, by the way. I'll have it linked up
there. Make sure you also watch the
pointers video because that's kind of
related as you're about to find out.
References are just pointers but with a
little bit more syntactic sugar and
slightly different semantics. References
are not something that you need to have
in the language from a functionality
point of view. You can achieve
everything you want to achieve with
references by just simply using
pointers. In fact, C, the language C,
doesn't have references. It's only got
pointers. So, let me rewrite this
without using references. I'm just going
to use pointers as if this was C.
Obviously, we have a vector here, which
is not C, but ignore that. So, I'll
change the reference to a pointer. And
then we're simply going to get the
memory address of fruits 0. This might
be revealing a little bit more about the
issue. Memory address of fruits zero. So
we are directly getting the memory
address of the string that is inside
this data structure. And then what can
happen when we decide to push something
else into the vector? It might have to
grow. It might have to resize. It might
have to reallocate memory. So if we
currently have a vector somewhere in our
memory with four elements in it, we have
our apple, orange, plum, and pear.
That's them over here. And then suddenly
we want to add this grapefruit. There's
no room for it. So it has to reallocate
that memory. What does that look like?
Well, it can vary, but let's just say
that it will find an entirely new block
of free memory somewhere else. It will
allocate at least enough space for all
of the elements that we now request to
be in that data structure. So in this
case, five. And then it will copy across
all of the elements into these new
blocks of memory. Not one at a time
hopefully. And then our grapefruit gets
put into here. Now our first fruit
pointer or reference doesn't matter.
This is pointing to here and this will
stay pointing to here no matter what we
do with the vector because it's pointing
to memory a memory address. It's not
some sort of alias for fruits zero and
it will remain that way. No, it's that
actual fixed point in memory. And then
so obviously once all of this has been
copied, we have our brand new block of
memory. This is getting freed. It's
getting deleted. So now we still have
this variable pointing to deleted
memory, freed memory. Whereas what you
might expect if you just don't think
about it hard enough is that oh yeah, I
have my reference to you know fruits
zero. So it doesn't matter what happens
to the vector, it's always going to be
that first element in there. No. And
obviously this makes a lot more sense I
think if you just write it out like this
as a pointer because now it's like well
yeah this is the memory address of this
element and then if the vector
reallocates memory and that old memory
gets freed then this is now invalid. But
when you write things as references it
just might be something that you don't
expect. Should this mean that you
shouldn't use references in C++? Just
use pointers everywhere. No. You just
have to keep in mind that that's how
references work. They're just pointers
and you have to be aware of what exactly
you're referencing because ultimately
you're referencing memory. A safer way
to reference a particular element inside
this data structure would be by its
index. So for example, you could have
first fruit which is a little bit silly
in this case. You can set that to zero.
And so now you still have to access this
data structure but you have that
particular element in there that you
want to access. Probably makes a bit
more sense if we say something like
plum. like we want to be referencing the
plum which is at index 2. That means
that no matter where we are before or
after this memory reallocation, it
doesn't matter. We're still going to be
correct unless that element actually
moves within the data structure, which
could happen if we insert something
between origin plum because then plum
would be index 3. But this is the much
safer way to do this compared to just
taking a reference. You can still do
this, but you just have to be mindful.
You just have to be careful of, hey, I'm
addressing memory directly and that
memory may move. Want to have a
dashboard of information at a glance
without getting distracted or losing
focus? Check out Terminal, the sponsor
of this video. Terminal is an e- in
dashboard companion that helps you stay
focused. It's just this small,
convenient open platform display with a
battery that lasts between 2 months and
1/2 years. Oh, and it's super
affordable. Available from just $139.
It's a great way to display whatever
information you like anywhere in your
house. You could show your calendar or
the weather in the kitchen for the whole
family to see, for example, or you could
take it to your office and display some
workrelated information. Put it wherever
you like. I've had it for the last month
or so, and I really like it. The whole
family does. Terminal is powered by
plugins which display all of this
information on the screen. They
currently have over 78 first party
plugins and hundreds more private
plugins. And of course, you can easily
make your own. You can control how it
cycles between plugins to show different
information or create views that show
more than one plugin on the screen at
the same time. Terminal is available in
a wide range of colors. I have the white
one here. Click my link in description
below and check it out. Huge thank you
to Terminal for sponsoring this video.
Now, if this seems like a little bit of
a weird example and it seems like
something that it would never happen to
you because you don't take references of
variables within data structures,
another thing to consider is the fact
that if you just had a function over
here that maybe took in a string, how
would you take in that string? by const
reference most likely. So here for
example is a particular fruit that we
take in. If we simply pass in fruits
zero over here and then perhaps this
function modifies this fruits vector in
some way by adding an element to it then
this is still a reference that will
become invalid potentially and might be
a bomb just waiting to go off. Oh but
taking in const string references. What
is this like 2005? I would just use a
string view. That's like yeah that's you
know who uses const string references.
Well, that's the same thing. A string
view is just a pointer to the data with
a size. So, it's kind of like a string
pointer. It's pointing to memory inside
the string. So, if you have a string
that is allocated like this on the
stack, and the actual characters of the
string are small enough for small string
optimization, meaning that the actual
characters are just stored inside the
string class without having a pointer to
an external block of memory that
contains the actual data of the string.
then it's going to move and your string
view is going to become invalid just the
same way as a string reference would. So
if we take this and we just use a string
view here instead of a string and then I
just leave in the exact same code that I
had in the beginning, this is what's
going to happen. It's going to print
this. So it didn't actually crash but it
printed this which is obviously invalid
compared to if we do the printing before
pushing back the grapefruit and it
prints apple which is correct. So this
is the same concept. This is the same
problem. The moral of the story is that
whenever you take references or pointers
to actual blocks of memory, just be
aware that if those move, you're going
to be in trouble. Now, I realize that
this example in and of itself might be a
little bit silly because you might
think, who would do this realistically,
like in the real world, you probably
wouldn't take some kind of alias to
this, then add something to it like
this, and then print it. It seems a bit
weird, a bit fake. Well, here's another
example that I prepared, which I think
is a little bit more realistic. And I
have seen this happen in the real world.
We have a node strct here. It's just a
node in a tree. It's got a name and it's
got a vector of unsigned integers which
is just indices to other nodes which are
this node's children. We have a vector
of nodes. This is our actual data
structure. And then we're going to build
the tree by creating a bunch of nodes.
So let's push back this root node. And
then we want to push back child one and
child two. But we obviously need to add
those children to the root nodes
children structure. And it's obviously
going to be annoying to keep referring
to the root node by just nodes zero all
the time like this. So instead, why not
just create an alias to it? We'll just
create a reference and then we'll also
add the indices of these nodes that
we're creating into that root nodes
children. Seems great. But you can
probably see the problem here. We're
creating this node reference to node
zero, but then we're obviously modifying
the nodes data structure itself. So as
soon as we do this, this will basically
become invalid. The other problem with
this whole situation, by the way, is
that it's not exactly deterministic
because we don't know how many times the
vector will resize. We do have some
control over that, but it's not like
every time we add something to this
node's data structure, it will
reallocate memory. We could even fix the
bug here potentially by just saying,
let's reserve three elements worth of
memory here. So, we have enough memory
for this. So, therefore, this will
technically be valid because the memory
is not moving. And that's also part of
the problem. It's inconsistent. It's
hard to tell whether or not this will
end up being a problem. So, the solution
would be just to not use this root alias
even though it looks nice and instead
just use node zero. The other
possibility is you might have a function
that does in fact return a node
reference called get root node or
something like that and then that will
just return nodes zero. And then the
idea is that every single time you need
that root node, you call the get root
node function and then that will always
work because yes, it's returning a
reference, but every time you call it,
it's going to look up node zero and give
you a reference to that, which again is
the same as just writing this. But you
may prefer the look of that and there's
no like zero index floating around. I
could see why some people would prefer
either of these two options. Another
random example off the top of my head is
with strings. If I even have a string
that has like, I don't know, a bunch of
text in it, I might want to access a
particular character in there.
Obviously, there's not 50 characters in
here, but maybe I'm just accessing one
of these characters. And then I'm going
to keep adding to it. It might have to
reallocate it memory. A string is really
just a data structure. It's kind of like
a vector. So then accessing this C
variable, this reference to a particular
point inside here is going to
potentially be dangerous. undefined
behavior might result in a crash
depending on what it is you actually do
with this string. Let me know in the
comment section below if you've
encountered this kind of bug before. If
you have some other examples, feel free
to share them as well. I've got a pretty
long list of bugs for this series, but
if you have some suggestions, leave them
in the comment section below. Hope you
guys enjoy this video and this new idea
for a series. If you did, please don't
forget to hit the like button and I will
see you next time. Goodbye. you.